Hello, welcome back to our course. Today, we are going to talk about reading and writing data.
There are many sources of data. We could think about data in human-readable format, like CSV or TXT,
data in binary format, like Excel, SPSS, STATA, or data from relational databases like Oracle and SAP.
And R has more than 100 built-in datasets, which can be displayed by executing
ls("package:datasets"). So here you can see very first few
datasets in R, and actually many packages provide their own datasets.
Data() shows all datasets of loaded packages. So here, of course, an example. If we, for example, call data(iris),
then this loads dataset IRIS.
And then here, if we'd like to see how these data look like,
we could basically apply a function head() to iris, and then we can just see the first
4 rows. So you can see that this is a dataset with different species of irises.
And these species actually differ by sepal and petal
lengths, and widths. And, as you can see, a class of this dataset is a data frame, so you can see that data frames are indeed very useful.
How can we handle external data not data already included in R, but external data? Well,
we have two main functions for doing that, read.table() and write.table(),
a very general function and for all kinds of text-based data.
And we also have read.csv, and write.csv, this is for CSV files.
And then there are also specific functions for reading data from Excel, SQL, and they are available through specific packages.
So let us study in detail, the syntax of the function read.table.
So first, we need to select the file. The file is the name of the file to be read.
Then, we have this parameter header. It's a logical value indicating whether the file contains the names of the variables or not.
sep is the field separator character, so basically we tell R
what was the character for separating different variables. Was it a tabulated file? Was it a comma, semicolon, space, etc?
That stands for the decimal point used for, basically, reading the digits of a number.
And row.names is a vector of row names. And similarly, the syntax is very similar for read.csv.
When it comes to write.table, the syntax is similar, but before even file, we have this X. X is the object to be written. Imagine that we are programming, and then we
had a data frame we wanted to save, that would be that X.
Then the file is once again a character string naming the file
including the file extension. Separator string is, here denoted by SEP,
Na is the string to use for missing values in our data.
Dec is once again a character to use in the file for decimal points.
And row.names, it's a logical variable. Default is TRUE, so if we don't want to have our
rows named one two, I don't know, the number of the rows, we just indicate row.names
FALSE. And similar syntax is valid for write.csv. How can we access
folders, for example, to then write a specific directory for our file?
Per default, R accesses your working directory to read or write data.
If you'd like to access a file in a subfolder, you can just write file, and then in this quotation mark
.\ the name of this subfolder, and the name of the file.
If you would like to access a file in the parent directory,
then, we have this ..\ and my file.
We could, of course, type the entire file path
if our file is not either in this subfolder or in the parent folder.
And now here we have an example, so here we would like to read a table, we would like to read a file called iris.txt.
The header of this file is TRUE, meaning that we have the names of the variables.
Separator is a space, decimal point is dot. And row names, we don't have them, so NULL.
The class of the iris is data.frame. And we could see that, indeed,
we have, a data frame with different variables
and different rows as observations. The dimension of our dataset can be checked applying function DIM to the iris, so we can see that it's 150 rows
and 5 columns. And now, if I would like to create a new dataset, for example, I would like to create a
subset of my dataset, we could, apply bracketing here. So, I would like to now create a subset
of data, in which, sepal.length is larger equal to 3. How do I do it? Well, I
open the bracket next to the name of my dataset. And then I select
those rows for which sepal.width was larger equal than 3, and this is on the first place of my
first bracket. And then we leave the second place in the bracket empty.
And now we can see that indeed the dimension of my new
dataset is smaller. And now, if I would like to write this
table, this dataset, to any file, how do I proceed? I first select
what I like to write, so this is our object, this is our data frame, so this is new.diris
Then I select the name of the file
and iris.txt, then a separator, that would be a space. How do I handle missing data? So we call missing data NAs.
Decimal point is a dot, and row names is FALSE, because I wouldn't like to have any
row names in my new data set. And this is a summary function. Summary function is useful for checking some summary statistics
for variables in our dataset, so you can see that if I apply this function to our dataset,
I have some general summary statistics for each variable, I have minimum, I have two quartiles, I have median, I have mean,
and I have maximum. And for the last column, you can see that this is
not a numeric variable, so we can see that we have length,
we have a class, and we have a mode of this particular variable.
And when it comes to reading files in R from other sources,
there are specific packages for that. For example, for reading Excel files, we have a package, xlsx
or read_excel(). For SPSS files, we can select a
function from package foreign. For SAS files, we have a sas7bdat file package,
and for EViews, we have another package hexView, etc. So, you can see that R is very flexible when it comes to reading data from various sources.
Okay, that's it for today. Thank you, and see you in the next video.